Two years ago, I was invited as an artist
قبل سنتين تمت دعوتي
to participate in an exhibition commemorating
للمشاركة في معرض يحتفي
100 years of Islamic art in Europe.
بمئة سنة من الفن الإسلامي في أوروبا.
The curator had only one condition:
كان للقيم شرط واحد فقط:
I had to use the Arabic script for my artwork.
كان علي استخدام الخط العربي في عملي الفني.
Now, as an artist, a woman, an Arab,
الآن وكفنانة أنثى عربية
or a human being living in the world in 2010,
أو كإنسانة تعيش في العالم سنة 2010
I only had one thing to say:
كان لدي أمر واحد لأقوله:
I wanted to say no.
أردت أن أقول لا.
And in Arabic, to say "no," we say "no,
وباللغة العربية، لقول "لا، نقول "لا
and a thousand times no."
وألف لا".
So I decided to look for a thousand different noes.
فقررت أن أبحث عن ألف "لا" مختلفة.
on everything ever produced
من كل ما تم إنتاجه قط
under Islamic or Arab patronage in the past 1,400 years,
والمحسوب على ما هو عربي أو إسلامي في السنوات ال 1400 الماضية،
from Spain to the borders of China.
من إسبانيا إلى الصين.
I collected my findings in a book,
وجمعت نتاج بحثي في كتاب،
placed them chronologically, stating the name,
واضعة إياهم في ترتيب زمني, بذكر الإسم،
the patron, the medium and the date.
المسؤول عن العمل والمواد التي استعملت، المكان و الزمان.
Now, the book sat on a small shelf next to the installation,
والكتاب وضع على رف صغير قرب التثبيت
which stood three by seven meters, in Munich, Germany,
الذي يقف على علو سبعة أمتار في ميونيخ بألمانيا،
in September of 2010.
في سبتمبر سنة 2010.
Now, in January, 2011, the revolution started,
الآن في يناير سنة 2011، بدأت الثورة،
and life stopped for 18 days,
فتوقفت الحياة ل18 يوما،
and on the 12th of February,
وفي ال12 من فبراير،
we naively celebrated on the streets of Cairo,
احتفلنا بسذاجة في شوارع القاهرة،
believing that the revolution had succeeded.
معتقدين بأن الثورة قد نجحت.
Nine months later I found myself spraying messages
بعد 9 أشهر وجدت نفسي أرش رسائل
in Tahrir Square. The reason for this act
في ساحة التحرير. وسبب هذا العمل
was this image that I saw in my newsfeed.
هي الصورة التي وجدت في تغذيتي الإخبارية.
I did not feel that I could live in a city
لم أعتقده أنه بإمكاني العيش في مدينة
where people were being killed
حيث يقتل الناس
and thrown like garbage on the street.
ويرمون كالنفايات في الشارع.
So I took one "no" off a tombstone from
فأخذت "لا" على شكل علامة قبر
the Islamic Museum in Cairo, and I added a message to it:
من المتحف الإسلامي في القاهرة, وأضفت عبارة:
"no to military rule."
"لا لحكم العسكر".
And I started spraying that on the streets in Cairo.
وبدأت برشها على جدران شوارع القاهرة.
But that led to a series of no, coming out of the book
لكن ذلك قاد إلى سلسلة من اللاءات, جاءت من الكتاب
like ammunition, and adding messages to them,
كذخيرة، وأضفت لها عبارات،
and I started spraying them on the walls.
ثم بدأت برشها على الجدران.
So I'll be sharing some of these noes with you.
وسأقوم بمشاركة بعض هذه اللاءات معكم.
No to a new Pharaoh, because whoever comes next
لا لفرعون جديد، لأنه أيا كان من سيأتي لاحقا
should understand that we will never be ruled by another dictator.
يجب أن يفهم أننا لن نخضع لحكم ديكتاتور آخر.
No to violence: Ramy Essam came to Tahrir
لا للعنف: رامي عصام من ساحة التحرير
on the second day of the revolution,
في اليوم الثاني من الثورة،
and he sat there with this guitar, singing.
وقد جلس هناك بغيتاره، يغني.
One month after Mubarak stepped down, this was his reward.
بعد شهر من تنحي مبارك، كان هذا جزاءه.
No to blinding heroes. Ahmed Harara lost his right eye
لا لإعماء الأبطال. أحمد حرارا فقد عينه اليمنى
on the 28th of January,
في ال28 من يناير،
and he lost his left eye on the 19th of November,
وقد فقد عينه اليسرى في ال19 من نوفمبر،
by two different snipers.
من طرف قناصين مختلفين.
No to killing, in this case no to killing men of religion,
لا للقتل, وفي هذه الحالة، لا لقتل رجال الدين،
because Sheikh Ahmed Adina Refaat was shot
لأن الشيخ أحمد أدينا رفعت أصيب بالرصاص
on December 16th, during a demonstration,
في ال16 من ديسمبر, خلال مظاهرة،
leaving behind three orphans and a widow.
تاركا وراءه 3 أيتام وأرملة.
No to burning books. The Institute of Egypt was burned
لا لحرق الكتب. المعهد المصري تم حرقه
on December 17th, a huge cultural loss.
في ال17 من ديسمبر، وكانت خسارة ثقافية فادحه.
No to stripping the people,
لا لتعرية الناس،
and the blue bra is to remind us of our shame
والصدرية الزرقاء لتذكيرنا بعارنا
as a nation when we allow a veiled woman to be stripped
كأمة حين نسمح بأن تتم تعرية امرأة محجبة
and beaten on the street, and the footprint reads,
وضربها في الشارع, والملاحظة السفلية تقول
"Long live a peaceful revolution,"
"تعيش الثورة السلمية".
because we will never retaliate with violence.
لأننا لن ننتقم أبدا بعنف.
No to barrier walls. On February 5th,
لا لجدران العزل. في ال5 من فبراير،
concrete roadblocks were set up in Cairo
تم تثبيت حواجز طرقية اسمنتية في القاهرة
to protect the Ministry of Defense from protesters.
لحماية وزارة الداخلية من المتظاهرين.
Now, speaking of walls, I want to share with you the story
الآن، وبالحديث عن الجدران, أريد أن أشارككم قصة
of one wall in Cairo.
جدار في القاهرة.
A group of artists decided to paint a life-size tank
قرر مجموعة من الفنانين رسم دبابة بحجم حقيقي
on a wall. It's one to one.
على جدار. بمقياس مطابق.
In front of this tank there's a man on a bicycle
أمام هذه الدبابة هناك رجل على دراجة
with a breadbasket on his head. To any passerby,
وسلة خبز على رأسه. وبالنسبة لأي عابر
there's no problem with this visual.
فإنه لا يوجد أدنى مشكلة في الرسم.
After acts of violence, another artist came,
وبعد أعمال عنف جاء فنان آخر
painted blood, protesters being run over by the tank,
ورسم دما ومحتجين تدهسهم الدبابة
demonstrators, and a message that read,
ومتظاهرين، ورسالة تقول،
"Starting tomorrow, I wear the new face,
"بدء من الغد، فإنني ألبس وجها جديدا،
the face of every martyr. I exist."
وجه كل شهيد. أنا موجود."
Authority comes, paints the wall white,
فجاءت السلطة وبيضوا الجدار،
leaves the tank and adds a message:
تاركين الدبابة ومضيفين رسالة تقول:
"Army and people, one hand. Egypt for Egyptians."
"الجيش والشعب، يد واحدة. مصر للمصريين".
Another artist comes, paints the head of the military
فيأتي فنان آخر ويرسم رئيس الجيش
as a monster eating a maiden in a river of blood
كوحش يأكل فتاة في نهر من دم
in front of the tank.
أمام الدبابة.
Authority comes, paints the wall white, leaves the tank,
فتأتي السلطة ويبيضون الجدار تاركين الدبابة،
leaves the suit, and throws a bucket of black paint
واللباس العسكري, ويرمون بدله صباغة سوداء
just to hide the face of the monster.
فقط لتغطية وجه الوحش.
So I come with my stencils, and I spray them on the suit,
فجئت بقوالبي وبخختها على البذلة،
on the tank, and on the whole wall,
وعلى الدبابة وعلى سائر الجدار
and this is how it stands today
وهذا ما يبدو عليه اليوم
until further notice. (Laughter)
حتى إشعار آخر. (ضحك)
Now, I want to leave you with a final no.
الآن, أريد ترككم مع "لا" أخيرة.
I found Neruda scribbled on a piece of paper
وجدت عملا لنيرودا مخربشا على قطعة ورق
in a field hospital in Tahrir, and I decided to take a no of
في مستشفى ميداني في ميدان التحرير, وقررت أن آخذ لاء من
Mamluk Mausoleum in Cairo.
الضريح المملوكي في القاهرة.
The message reads,
تقول الرسالة،
[Arabic]
[العربية]
"You can crush the flowers, but you can't delay spring."
"يمكنك أن تدهس الورود لكنك لا تستطيع أن تؤخر الربيع."
Thank you. (Applause)
شكرا لكم. (تصفيق)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you. Shukran. (Applause)
شكرا لكم. 'شكرا' (تصفيق)